My journey to become a polar specialist,
إن رحتلي في أن أغدو متخصص في أمور القطب الشمالي
photographing, specializing in the polar regions,
ومصوراً للمناطق الجليدية
began when I was four years old,
بدأت عندما كنت في الرابعة من عمري
when my family moved from southern Canada
عندما انتقلت عائلتي من جنوب كندا
to Northern Baffin Island, up by Greenland.
الى القسم الشمالي من جزيرة بافين في جرين لاند
There we lived with the Inuit
كنا نعيش هناك مع الاسكيمو
in the tiny Inuit community of 200 Inuit people,
في مجتمع اسكيمو صغير يتكون من 200 شخص
where [we] were one of three non-Inuit families.
لقد كنا عائلة من بين 3 عائلات فقط تعيش هناك مع اهل الاسكيمو
And in this community, we didn't have a television;
وعندما كنا مع ذلك المجتمع لم نكن نملك التلفاز
we didn't have computers, obviously, radio.
ولا الحواسيب .. ولا حتى الراديو
We didn't even have a telephone.
حتى الهاتف لم نكن نملكه
All of my time was spent outside
وكنت أقضي معظم وقتي في الفناء
with the Inuit, playing.
مع اهل الاسكيمو .. ألعب معهم
The snow and the ice were my sandbox,
كان الثلج والجليد هما " رمل اللعب " خاصتي
and the Inuit were my teachers.
وكان اهل الاسكيمو أساتذتي
And that's where I became
وهناك أصبحت
truly obsessed with this polar realm.
مهووساً حقاً بعالم القطب الشمالي
And I knew someday that I was going to do something
وعلمت أنني في يوم ما سوف أقوم بشيء
that had to do with trying to share news about it
سيساعد على حمايته
and protect it.
ونقل رسالته - القطب الشمالي -
I'd like to share with you, for just two minutes only,
واريد ان اشارككم بدقيقتين فحسب
some images, a cross-section of my work,
من بعض الصور وبعض اللقطات من عملي
to the beautiful music by Brandi Carlile, "Have You Ever."
مع غناء " براندي كارلي " - هل حاولت ذات يوم -
I don't know why National Geographic has done this, they've never done this before,
في الحقيقة " ناشيونال جيوغرافيك " لم تسمح بهذا من ذي قبل - الصور ملكٌ لها -
but they're allowing me to show you a few images
ولكنهم قد سمحوا لي بأن اشارككم ببعض الصور
from a coverage that I've just completed that is not published yet.
من تغطيتي التي قمت بها في القطب الشمالي والتي لم تنشر بعد
National Geographic doesn't do this,
" ناشيونال جيوغرافيك " عادة لا تسمح بذلك
so I'm very excited to be able to share this with you.
لذا انا متحمس جداً لكي اتشاركها معكم
And what these images are --
والصور التي سوف ترونها
you'll see them at the start of the slide show -- there's only about four images --
في بداية العرض . . الاربع صور الاولى
but it's of a little bear that lives in the Great Bear Rainforest.
هي لدب صغير يعيش في غابة الدببة الكبرى
It's pure white, but it's not a polar bear.
انه أبيض نقي جداً .. انه ليس دب قطبي
It's a spirit bear, or a Kermode bear.
انه دب روحي و يدعى في بعض حين دب كيرمود
There are only 200 of these bears left.
وهناك 200 دب من هذا الفصيل فحسب
They're more rare than the panda bear.
وهذا الفصيل نادر اكثر من دببة البندا
I sat there on the river for two months without seeing one.
في تغطيتي هناك جلست مايقارب شهرين بانتظار ان ارى واحد من هذه الدببة
I thought, my career's over.
قلت لنفسي يبدو ان عملي قد انتهى
I proposed this stupid story to National Geographic.
كان من المفروض ان أأتي بصور لذلك الدب ل " ناشيونال جيوغرافيك "
What in the heck was I thinking?
ولكن بماذا كنت افكر ؟
So I had two months to sit there
جلست لمدة شهرين
and figure out different ways of what I was going to do in my next life,
احاول ان اجد شيئاً اقوم به بعد ان يتم فصلي من العمل
after I was a photographer, because they were going to fire me.
وكيف يمكن ان اعمل مصوراً في مجالات اخرى
Because National Geographic is a magazine; they remind us all the time:
لان " ناشيونال جيوغرافيك " تذكرنا دوماً
they publish pictures, not excuses.
انها تنشر الصور .. لا الأعذار !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And after two months of sitting there --
وبعد شهرين من الجلوس هناك
one day, thinking that it was all over,
ذات يوم .. وحينما كنت غارقاً في التفكير فيما بعد هذه الوظيفة
this incredible big white male came down,
جاء دب أبيض مهيب
right beside me, three feet away from me,
وتوقف بالقرب مني تماما .. على بعد 3 اقدام
and he went down and grabbed a fish and went off in the forest and ate it.
ومن ثم قام باصطياد سمكة وعاد الى الغابة وأكلها
And then I spent the entire day living my childhood dream
ومن ثم قضيت جل ذلك اليوم وانا اعيش حلم الطفولة
of walking around with this bear through the forest.
وانا اسير بالقرب من الدب عبر الغابات
He went through this old-growth forest
لقد سرت خلفه الى غابة قديمة
and sat up beside this 400-year-old culturally modified tree and went to sleep.
وجلست مستظلاً بشجرة عمرها 400 عام .. وغافلني النوم حينها ..
And I actually got to sleep within three feet of him,
في الحقيقة نمت على بعد 3 اقدام منه
just in the forest, and photograph him.
في تلك الغابة .. وقد التقطت الكثير من الصور له
So I'm very excited to be able to show you those images
وانا متحمس جداً لكي أريكم هذه الصور
and a cross-section of my work that I've done on the polar regions.
عن بعض من أعمالي .. في القطب الشمالي .. ونحوه
Please enjoy.
إستمتعوا بهذا العرض
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Brandi Carlile: ♫ Have you ever wandered lonely through the woods? ♫
براندي كارلي : ♫هل تجولت يوماً في الغابات♫
♫ And everything there feels just as it should ♫
♫وكل شيء بدا من حولك رائعاً♫
♫ You're part of the life there ♫
♫وشعرت بنفسك جزءا من تلك الغابة♫
♫ You're part of something good ♫
♫جزءا من شيء رائع ♫
♫ If you've ever wandered lonely through the woods ♫
♫هل تجولت يوماً وحيداً في الغابات♫
♫ Ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh ♫
♫آوووه , آووه , آووووه♫
♫ Have you ever stared into a starry sky? ♫
♫هل تأملت يوماً السماء♫
♫ Lying on your back, you're asking why ♫
♫هل استلقيت يوماً وتسائلت لماذا ♫
♫ What's the purpose? ♫
♫ما الهدف ♫
♫ I wonder, who am I? ♫
♫انا أتساءل من أنا♫
♫ If you've ever stared into a starry sky ♫
♫هل نظرت يوماً إلى السماء ♫
♫ Ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh ♫
♫آوووه , آووه , آووووه♫
♫ Aah, ah, aah ♫
♫♫آوووه , آووه , آووووه♫
♫ Have you ever stared into a starry sky? ♫
♫هل نظرت يوماً إلى السماء ♫
♫ Have you ever been out walking in the snow? ♫
♫هل سرت ذات يوم بين الثلوج♫
♫ Tried to get back where you were before ♫
♫محاولاً ان تبحث عن نفسك في الازمان♫
♫ You always end up ♫
♫تنتهي بك الامور دوماً♫
♫ Not knowing where to go ♫
♫دون ان تعرف الى اين الطريق♫
♫ If you've ever been out walking in the snow ♫
♫هل تجولت يوماً بين الثلوج♫
♫ Ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh ♫
♫آوووه , آووه , آووووه♫
♫ If you'd ever been out walking you would know ♫
♫ان تجولت يوماً فسوف تعرف الاجابة ♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Paul Nicklen: Thank you very much. The show's not over.
بول نيكلين : شكراً .. شكراً جزيلاً لكم .. لم ينتهي العرض بعد
My clock is ticking. OK, let's stop.
وقت المحادثة يسير بسرعة ..
Thank you very much. I appreciate it.
شكراً جزيلا لكم .. انا اقدر هذا ..
We're inundated with news all the time
نحن نسمع طيلة الوقت على محطات الاخبار
that the sea ice is disappearing
ان البحر المتجمد يتلاشى
and it's at its lowest level.
وان مستواه ينخفض
And in fact, scientists were originally saying
في الحقيقة ان العلماء يقولون
sea ice is going to disappear in the next hundred years, then they said 50 years.
ان البحر المتجمد سوف يختفي في ال100 عام القادمة .. ومن ثم توقعوا في ال50 عام القادمة
Now they're saying the sea ice in the Arctic,
والان هو يقولون ان البحر في القطب
the summertime extent is going to be gone in the next four to 10 years.
ومع امتداد فترة الصيف فانه قد يتلاشى من 4-10 سنوات
And what does that mean?
ولكن ماذا يعني هذا
After a while of reading this in the news, it just becomes news.
بعد ان تسمع هذه الاخبار لفترة طويلة فانها تغدو
You glaze over with it.
مجرد اخبار .. تمر عليها مرور الكرام .. دون أن تعباً بها
And what I'm trying to do with my work is put faces to this.
وما احاول ان اقوم به في عملي هو ان القي بالضوء على هذه المشكلة
And I want people to understand and get the concept
من اجل ان يعي الناس المشكلة
that, if we lose ice,
علينا ان نعي انه في حال خسرنا الجليد
we stand to lose an entire ecosystem.
فاننا سوف نخسر نظاماً بيئياً بأكمله
Projections are that we could lose polar bears, they could become extinct
ان المتنبؤن يقولون ان الدب القطبي سوف ينقرض
in the next 50 to 100 years.
خلال ال 50-100 سنة القادمة
And there's no better, sexier,
ان هذه الدببة هي الاجمل
more beautiful, charismatic megafauna species
والاروع والاكثر سحرية بين كل المخلوقات
for me to hang my campaign on.
وهي التي تجعلني استمر في عملي
Polar bears are amazing hunters.
ان الدببة القطبية مفترسة بارعة
This was a bear I sat with for a while on the shores.
وهذا دب كنت اراقبه على الشاطىء
There was no ice around.
لم يكن هناك جليد في تلك المنطقة
But this glacier caved into the water and a seal got on it.
ولكن كان هناك كهف جليدي في المياه .. ودخلت اليه فقمة البحر
And this bear swam out to that seal --
فقفز الدب خلف فقمة البحر وسبح
800 lb. bearded seal --
وافترسها .. انها تزن 800 رطل
grabbed it, swam back and ate it.
امسك بها وعاد بها الى الشاطىء
And he was so full, he was so happy and so fat eating this seal,
وقد اكل كفايته حينها .. كان سعيداً جداً
that, as I approached him --
لدرجة انني حين اقتربت منه ..
about 20 feet away -- to get this picture,
على بعد 20 قدم لالتقاط هذه الصورة
his only defense was to keep eating more seal.
لم يكن رده على هذا التصرف الا بالاكل اكثر
And as he ate, he was so full --
لقد اكل .. واكل .. وامتلأ
he probably had about 200 lbs of meat in his belly --
ربما التهم اكثر من 200 رطل من اللحم
and as he ate inside one side of his mouth,
حيث كان يقطع في احد اطراف فمه
he was regurgitating out the other side of his mouth.
ويهضم ويسحق في الطرف الآخر من الفم
So as long as these bears have any bit of ice they will survive,
ان هذه الدببة بدون وجود الجليد لن تكون قادرة على البقاء
but it's the ice that's disappearing.
ان اختفى الجليد سوف تختفي
We're finding more and more dead bears in the Arctic.
نحن نجد اليوم تلو اليوم المزيد من الدببة التي قضي نحبها في القطب
When I worked on polar bears as a biologist 20 years ago,
ان طيلة فترة عملي على مدى ال20 عام
we never found dead bears.
لم اكن اصدف دببة نافقة بهذا الكم
And in the last four or five years,
وفي السنوات الاربعة و الخمس الماضية
we're finding dead bears popping up all over the place.
بدأنا نجد الكثير من الدببة النافقة والتي تملأ المكان
We're seeing them in the Beaufort Sea,
غدونا نراهم في بحر بيفورت
floating in the open ocean where the ice has melted out.
وهم عائمون على سطحه جراء ذوبان غطاءه الجليدي
I found a couple in Norway last year. We're seeing them on the ice.
وجدت اثنين في النرويج السنة الماضية .. نحن نراهم على الجليد
These bears are already showing signs
ان هذه الدببة تشير الى مخاطر جمة
of the stress of disappearing ice.
والتي تنتج عن استنفاز المسطحات الجليدية
Here's a mother and her two year-old cub
هذه أم وابنها ابن العامين
were traveling on a ship a hundred miles offshore in the middle of nowhere,
يسافران على سفينة على بعد مئات الاميال من الشاطىء
and they're riding on this big piece of glacier ice,
وهم يسافران على قطعة الجليد الكبيرة هذه
which is great for them; they're safe at this point.
والتي سوف تنقلهم الى مكان آمن
They're not going to die of hypothermia.
ولن يموتا من الجفاف
They're going to get to land.
وسوف يصلان الى الشاطىء
But unfortunately, 95 percent of the glaciers in the Arctic
ولكن للاسف فان 95 % من المسطحات الجليدية في القطب
are also receding right now
تتآكل اليوم
to the point that the ice is ending up on land
من المسطحات الارضية
and not injecting any ice back into the ecosystem.
دون ان يكون هناك امداد عكسي للثلوج لتعويض ذلك
These ringed seals, these are the "fatsicles" of the Arctic.
هذه هي فقم الخواتم .. انها من عجائب القطب
These little, fat dumplings,
ان هذه الفقم الكسولة السمينة
150-pound bundles of blubber
والتي تزن نحو 150 رطلاً
are the mainstay of the polar bear.
هي الفريسة الاساسية للدب القطبي
And they're not like the harbor seals that you have here.
وهي ليست مثل فقم الساحل هنا
These ringed seals also live out their entire life cycle
انها فقم تعيش و تعتمد كل حياتها على الجليد
associated and connected to sea ice.
وهي مرتبطة به ارتباط تام
They give birth inside the ice,
فهي تلد داخل الجليد
and they feed on the Arctic cod that live under the ice.
وهي تتغذى على سمك القد في القطب الشمالي الذي يعيش اسفل الجليد
And here's a picture of sick ice.
وهذه صورة لمسطح جليدي
This is a piece of multi-year ice that's 12 years old.
وهذه القطعة من الجليد عمرها 12 عاماً
And what scientists didn't predict is that, as this ice melts,
ولم يتوقع العلماء ذوبانها بهذه السرعة
these big pockets of black water are forming
ان المسطحات الممتدة التي تتشكل على سطح الماء
and they're grabbing the sun's energy
تمتص مساحة اكبر من اشعة الشمس
and accelerating the melting process.
مما يسرع عملية الذوبان
And here we are diving in the Beaufort Sea.
وهنا نحن غائصون في بحر بفورت
The visibility's 600 ft.; we're on our safety lines;
وكان المشهد من على عمق 600 قدم .. وهي مسافة آمنة
the ice is moving all over the place.
لكي لا ننجرف مع حركة المسطحات الجليدية
I wish I could spend half an hour telling you
ويمكنني ان اقضي نصف ساعة اشرح
about how we almost died on this dive.
لكم كيف كان من الممكن ان نلقى حتفنا هناك
But what's important in this picture is that you have a piece of multi-year ice,
ولكن المهم في هذه الصورة .. هو ان هذه القطع الجليدية
that big chunk of ice up in the corner.
وخاصة في زواياها .. الكبيرة
In that one single piece of ice,
في تلك القطعة مثلاً
you have 300 species of microorganisms.
تجد اكثر من 300 فصيل من الكائنات الدقيقة
And in the spring, when the sun returns to the ice,
وفي الربيع عندما تطل الشمس على الجليد
it forms the phytoplankton, grows under that ice,
فان هذه الكائنات تشكل العوالق النباتية والتي تنمو اسف الجلد
and then you get bigger sheets of seaweed,
ومن ثم تكبر لتصبح اعشاب بحر
and then you get the zooplankton feeding on all that life.
ومن ثم تحصل على بلانكتونات كثيرة تغذي كل الحياة البحرية
So really what the ice does
ان الجليد في الحقيقة
is it acts like a garden.
يعمل عمل التربة
It acts like the soil in a garden. It's an inverted garden.
انه عبارة عن حديقة مقلوبة
Losing that ice is like losing the soil in a garden.
ان فقدان هذا الجليد .. يعني فقدان تربة البحار
Here's me in my office.
هذا هو مكتبي ..
I hope you appreciate yours.
اتمنى ان تقدروا مكاتبكم ..
This is after an hour under the ice.
هذه الصورة التقطت بعد ساعة من البقاء اسفل الجليد
I can't feel my lips; my face is frozen;
لم اكن اشعر بشفتي .. كان وجهي متجمد
I can't feel my hands; I can't feel my feet.
ولم اكن اشعر لا بقدمي ولا بيدي
And I've come up, and all I wanted to do was get out of the water.
وخرجت حينها وكل شيء في بالي كان ان اخرج من الماء
After an hour in these conditions,
فبعد ساعة من تلك البيئة الصعبة
it's so extreme that, when I go down,
المتطرفة .. في كل مرة اغوص فيها ..
almost every dive I vomit into my regulator
اصاب بوعكة صحية كبيرة
because my body can't deal with the stress of the cold on my head.
لان جسمي لا يستطيع ان يتعامل مع الاجهاد الناتج من انخفاض درجة الحرارة في الراس
And so I'm just so happy that the dive is over.
وانا سعيد جداً لان تلك الرحلة انتهت
I get to hand my camera to my assistant,
اعطيتي حينها كميرا التصوير لمساعدي
and I'm looking up at him, and I'm going, "Woo. Woo. Woo."
وانا انظر اليه اقول له " ها .. ها ها .. "
Which means, "Take my camera."
اقصد بها خذ كميرا التصوير خاصتي ..
And he thinks I'm saying, "Take my picture."
فاعتقد انني اقول " التقط لي صورة "
So we had this little communication breakdown.
يبدو اننا فقدنا القدرة على التواصل حينها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it's worth it.
ولكن الامر كان يستحق كل ذلك التعب
I'm going to show you pictures of beluga whales, bowhead whales,
اتعلمون يمكن ان اريكم صوراً لحيتان كبيرة .. وحيتان مميزة
and narwhals, and polar bears, and leopard seals today,
او دببة قطبية او فهود الفقمة
but this picture right here means more to me than any other I've ever made.
ولكن هذه الصورة تعني لي اكثر من كل تلك الصور
I dropped down in this ice hole, just through that hole that you just saw,
لقد غصت في حفرة الثلج .. ومن ثم سبحت عبرها
and I looked up under the underside of the ice,
ونظرت اسفل طبقة الجليد لكي ارى هذا المشهد الخلاب
and I was dizzy; I thought I had vertigo.
ظننت انني اشعر بدوار .. فقد كنت اشعر بالوخز
I got very nervous -- no rope, no safety line,
لقد اصبت بالتوتر .. اذ لم اكن مربوطاً بحبال الامان
the whole world is moving around me --
وكان العالم باكمله يتحرك من حولي
and I thought, "I'm in trouble."
وقلت في نفسي .. يبدو انني وقعت في ورطة
But what happened is that the entire underside
ولكن هذا ما رأيته .. لقد كان اسفل الطبقة الجليدية
was full of these billions of amphipods and copepods
ممتلئاً بثنائية الارجل والمجدفات
moving around and feeding on the underside of the ice,
وهم يتحركون بحركة دؤوبة ويتغذون على ما يوجد اسفل طبقة الجليد
giving birth and living out their entire life cycle.
ويتكاثرون .. ويقضون دورة حياتهم هناك
This is the foundation of the whole food chain in the Arctic, right here.
ان هذه المنطقة هي الاساس لكل الدورة الغذائية في القطب الشمالي
And when you have low productivity in this, in ice,
وعندما تقل انتاجيتها فان كل شيء في القطب
the productivity in copepods go down.
سوف يتأثر
This is a bowhead whale.
ان هذا الحوت القطبي
Supposedly, science is stating
يفترض انه بحسب الدراسات
that it could be the oldest living animal on earth right now.
اقدم حيوان يعيش على كوكب الارض
This very whale right here could be over 250 years old.
ان هذاالحوت هنا عمره قد يتجاوز ال 250 عاما
This whale could have been born
وهذا الحوت قد ولد
around the start of the Industrial Revolution.
تقريبا في بداية الثورة الصناعية
It could have survived 150 years of whaling.
وقد استطاع ان يستمر في الابحار طول تلك المدة
And now its biggest threat is the disappearance of ice in the North
ولكن اليوم الخطر الاكبر الذي يواجهه هو اختفاء طبقة الجليد في القطب الشمالي
because of the lives that we're leading in the South.
بسبب التصرفات التي تحدث من قبل البشر في الارض
Narwhals, these majestic narwhals
ذوي الرمح .. هذه الحيتان السحرية
with their eight-foot long ivory tusks, don't have to be here;
والتي تملك ناباً طويلاً بطول 8 اقدام .. لا يجب ان تكون هنا
they could be out on the open water.
يمكن ان تكون في المياه المفتوحة
But they're forcing themselves to come up in these tiny little ice holes
ولكنهم يأتون الى هنا لكي يخرجوا من تلك الفتحات الجليدية
where they can breathe, catch a breath,
من اجل الاستنشاق فحسب
because right under that ice are all the swarms of cod.
كما لانه اسفل الطبقات الجليدية يوجد العديد من اسماك القد
And the cod are there
والتي بدورها تتغذى
because they are feeding on all the copepods and amphipods.
على ثنائيات الارجل والمجدفات
Alright, my favorite part.
الان . .لننتقل الى جزء المفضل
When I'm on my deathbed,
عندما واجهت الموت تماما
I'm going to remember one story more than any other.
انا سوف اتذكر قصة واحدة من كل حياتي المهنية مهما تقدمت في العمر
Even though that spirit bear moment was powerful,
حتى اكثر من قصة الدب الابيض الروحانية المميزة
I don't think I'll ever have another experience
ولكن اعتقد ان التجربة التالية هي التي اثرت في اكثر مما سبق
like I did with these leopard seals.
والتي تخص فهود البحر
Leopard seals, since the time of Shackleton, have had a bad reputation.
ان فهود البحر منذ ايام " شاكيلتون " تملك سمعة سيئة
They've got that wryly smile on their mouth.
فهي لديها تلك الابتسامة المخيفة و الفم الغريب
They've got those black sinister eyes
وتلك الاعين السوداء المبهمة
and those spots on their body.
والنقاط المبعثرة على اجسادها
They look positively prehistoric and a bit scary.
وهي تبدو قادمة من التاريخ السحيق ومخيفة جداً
And tragically in [2003],
بالاضافة الى انه في عام 2004
a scientist was taken down and drowned,
تم سحب احد العلماء واغراقه
and she was being consumed by a leopard seal.
من قبل احدى فهود البحر
And people were like, "We knew they were vicious. We knew they were."
والناس أثبتوا فكرة انهم مخلوقات شريرة وقال البعض " كنا نعلم ذلك كنا نعلم "
And so people love to form their opinions.
ان الناس تحب ان تشكل الآراء
And that's when I got a story idea:
وهنا خطرت لي فكرة
I want to go to Antarctica,
اريد ان اذهب الى القطب المتجمد
get in the water with as many leopard seals as I possibly can
وان انزل الى المياه في المناطق الغنية بفهود البحر
and give them a fair shake --
لكي اكتشف ماهية حقيقة
find out if they really are these vicious animals, or if they're misunderstood.
ان هذه المخلوقات شريرة .. او انها قد فهمت بصورة خاطئة
So this is that story.
واليكم هذه القصة
Oh, and they also happen to eat Happy Feet.
نسيت ان اخبركم .. انهم يقتاتون على البطاريق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As a species, as humans, we like to say penguins are really cute,
كفصيل .. نحن البشر نحب ان نقول ان البطاريق هي حيوانات لطيفة
therefore, leopard seals eat them, so leopard seals are ugly and bad.
وعندما نعلم ان افهد البحر يقتات عليها .. فنصفه بانه قبيح وسيء
It doesn't work that way.
ولكن الامر لا يسير هكذا في الحياة
The penguin doesn't know it's cute,
ثم ان البطاريق لا تعلم انها لطيفة
and the leopard seal doesn't know it's kind of big and monstrous.
وفهود البحر لا تعلم انها بافتراس البطاريق تبدو وحوشاً
This is just the food chain unfolding.
وانها مجرد حلقة من حلقات السلسلة الغذائية
They're also big.
حسناً .. ان فهود البحر عملاقة ايضاً
They're not these little harbor seals.
انها ليست مثل فقم البحر
They are 12 ft. long, a thousand pounds.
انها بطول 12 قدم وبوزن 1000 رطل
And they're also curiously aggressive.
وهي عدائية وفضولية
You get 12 tourists packed into a Zodiac,
فان خرج 12 سائحاً على ظهر مركب
floating in these icy waters,
ضمن تلك المسطحات الجليدية
and a leopard seal comes up and bites the pontoon.
فان فهود البحر سوف تحيط بهم وتبدأ بقضم تلك العوامات
The boat starts to sink, they race back to the ship
ويبدا المركب بالغرق .. ومن ثم يسارعون في العودة الى الشاطىء
and get to go home and tell the stories of how they got attacked.
لكي يخبروا الناس والاصدقاء كيف ان فهود البحر هاجمتهم
All the leopard seal was doing --
وسعت الى اغراقهم ...بينما كل ما قامت به فهود البحر
it's just biting a balloon.
هي قضم عوامات المركب
It just sees this big balloon in the ocean -- it doesn't have hands --
انها ترى ذلك البالون الكبير في المحيط .. وهو لا يملك الايدي
it's going to take a little bite, the boat pops, and off they go.
فتحاول قضمه .. فينفجر .. فتعود ادارجها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So after five days of crossing the Drake Passage --
حسناً لقد استغرقنا 5 ايام ونحن نعبر ممر " دراك "
isn't that beautiful --
اليس هذا جميلاً
after five days of crossing the Drake Passage,
بعد خمسة ايام من عبور ممر " دراك "
we have finally arrived at Antarctica.
وصلنا اخيراً الى القطب المتجمد
I'm with my Swedish assistant and guide.
وانا كنت مع مساعدي السويدي ومرشدي
His name is Goran Ehlme from Sweden -- Goran.
واسمه جوران هلمي من السويد .. جوران
And he has a lot of experience with leopard seals. I have never seen one.
ولديه خبرة واسعة فيما يخص فهود البحر .. ولم اكن من قبل قد شهدت واحداً منها
So we come around the cove in our little Zodiac boat,
وقد ذهبنا عبر ممر جليدي بقارب طوف
and there's this monstrous leopard seal.
وكانت هناك فهود البحر الشريرة
And even in his voice, he goes, "That's a bloody big seal, ya."
وقد قائل المرشد " ها هي فهود البحر المفترسة "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this seal is taking this penguin by the head,
وها هو فهد بحر يفترس بطريقاً من راسه
and it's flipping it back and forth.
ومن ثم يقلبه يمنة ويسرة
And what it's trying to do is turn that penguin inside-out,
وهو يحاول ان يفصل رأسه عن جسده
so it can eat the meat off the bones,
من اجل ان يتمكن من اكل اللحم بدلا عن العظم
and then it goes off and gets another one.
ومن ثم يرميه ويحاول افتراس واحد آخر
And so this leopard seal grabbed another penguin,
وبينما هو يفترس واحد آخر
came under the boat, the Zodiac,
جاء الى اسفل قارب الطوف
starting hitting the hull of the boat.
وبدا يضرب قاع القارب
And we're trying to not fall in the water.
وحاولنا ان لا نسقط في المياه
And we sit down, and that's when Goran said to me,
ومن ثم جلسنا .. وقال لي جوران
"This is a good seal, ya.
" انه فهد بحر طيب .. ها !
It's time for you to get in the water."
عليك ان تنزل الان الى البحر "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I looked at Goran, and I said to him, "Forget that."
نظرت الى جوران .. وقلت له " إنسى الامر "
But I think I probably used a different word starting with the letter "F."
ولكن اظن انني حينها استخدمت كلمة اخرى غير تلك ربما تبدأ بحرف " الاف "
But he was right.
ولكنه كان مصيباً
He scolded me out, and said, "This is why we're here.
حين وبخني وقال " نحن هنا لهذا
And you purposed this stupid story to National Geographic.
انت من تقدم لناشيونل جيوغرافيك بهذا الاقتراح الغبي
And now you've got to deliver.
وعليك ان تنفذه
And you can't publish excuses."
لا يمكنك ان تنشر الاعذار "
So I had such dry mouth --
حينها قد جف حلقي
probably not as bad as now --
ليس كما هي حالي الان .. لانني تحدثت كثيراً
but I had such, such dry mouth.
ولكن فعلاً كان قد جف حلقي
And my legs were just trembling. I couldn't feel my legs.
وكانت ارجلي ترتجف .. لم اكن اشعر بها
I put my flippers on. I could barely part my lips.
فوضعت " الزعانف " و بصعوبة كنت احرك شفتي
I put my snorkel in my mouth,
ومن ثم وضعت جهاز التنفس على فمي
and I rolled over the side of the Zodiac into the water.
وقفزت من على القارب الى مياه المحيط
And this was the first thing she did.
واول شيء قامت به " فهدة البحر "
She came racing up to me, engulfed my whole camera --
هو انها جرت نحوي واجتاحت الكميرا
and her teeth are up here and down here --
وها هي اسنانها تتضح لكم
but Goran, before I had gotten in the water, had given me amazing advice.
ولكن جوران .. قبل ان انزل الى المياه اعطاني نصيحة مميزة
He said, "If you get scared, you close your eyes, ya, and she'll go away."
قال لي .. ان خفت .. عليك ان تغلق عينيك .. وسوف يختفي فهد البحر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that's all I had to work with at that point.
وكان كل ما يجب ان اقوم به حين ذلك
But I just started to shoot these pictures.
وبدأت ان ااخذ هذه الصور
So she did this threat display for a few minutes,
وقامت بهذا " التصرف " المهدد لعدة دقائق
and then the most amazing thing happened -- she totally relaxed.
ومن ثم حدث شيء مميز حينها .. -- لقد استقرت
She went off, she got a penguin.
ومن ثم ابتعدت .. واحضرت بطريقاً
She stopped about 10 feet away from me,
وتوقفت على بعد 10 اقدام مني
and she sat there with this penguin, the penguin's flapping, and she let's it go.
ومن ثم جلست مع البطريق .. واخذت تقلب البطريق .. ومن ثم تركته ..
The penguin swims toward me, takes off.
فاندفع البطريق نحوي ..
She grabs another one. She does this over and over.
ومن ثم احضرت بطريقاً اخر . .. واخذت تقوم بهذا على الدوام
And it dawned on me that she's trying to feed me a penguin.
ومن ثم اقتربت مني وحاولت اطعامي البطريق
Why else would she release these penguins at me?
والا لماذا كانت ترمي البطاريق نحوي
And after she did this four or five times,
وبعد 4 او 5 محاولات
she swam by me with this dejected look on her face.
سبحت نحوي بهذه النظرة الغريبة على وجهها
You don't want to be too anthropomorphic, but I swear that she looked at me
لا اريد ان اكون دراماتيكيا جدا.. ولكنها نظرت نحوي وتوهمت انها قالت في نفسها
like, "This useless predator's going to starve in my ocean."
ان لم يكن هذا الشيء مفترساً .. سوف يموت جوعاً في المحيط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So realizing I couldn't catch swimming penguins,
وقد ادركت انني لا استطيع السباحة و امساك البطاريق
she'd get these other penguins and bring them slowly towards me,
وبدات بتلقف البطاريق ومن ثم تقريبها مني
bobbing like this, and she'd let them go.
تحركهم هكذا .. ومن ثم تتركهم
This didn't work.
ولم ينجح هذا
I was laughing so hard and so emotional
كنت اضحك بشدة .. وكانت عواطفي متقدة
that my mask was flooding, because I was crying underwater,
وكان قناعي يمتلىء بالماء لانني كنت ابكي في الاعماق
just because it was so amazing.
لقد كان موقفا رائعاً
And so that didn't work.
ولكن هذا لم يسر معها جيداً
So then she'd get another penguin and try this ballet-like sexy display
ومن ثم احضرت بطريقاً آخراً .. وقامت بحركة باليه مميزة
sliding down this iceberg like this. (Laughter)
كما تلك التي يقوم بها الراقصون على الجليد
And she would sort of bring them over to me and offer it to me.
وكان تحاول ان تقدم لي البطاريق بعدة صور
This went on for four days.
وقد استمر هذا ل 4 ايام
This just didn't happen a couple of times.
اكثر من مرة
And then so she realized I couldn't catch live ones,
ومن ثم ادركت انني لا استطيع ان افترس بطاريق على قيد الحياة
so she brought me dead penguins.
لذا احضرت لي بطريقاً ميتاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now I've got four or five penguins floating around my head,
وقد كان هناك 4-5 بطاريق ميتة تحوم حولي
and I'm just sitting there shooting away.
وانا كنت هناك التقط الصور
And she would often stop and have this dejected look on her face
ومن ثم توقفت وادركت انني اصدها .. وشعرت بهذا على وجهها
like, "Are you for real?"
فتقدمت وقالت " هل انت حقيقي ؟ "
Because she can't believe I can't eat this penguin.
لانها لم تكن تستطيع ان تصدق انني لا استطيع أكل البطاريق
Because in her world, you're either breeding or you're eating --
لان في عالمها الكائنات نوعاً .. اما مفترس .. او مُفترس
and I'm not breeding, so ...
وانا لست مفترساً على ما يبدو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then that wasn't enough; she started to flip penguins onto my head.
ولكنها لم تتوقف عند هذا .. بدات تدير البطاريق فوق راسي
She was trying to force-feed me. She's pushing me around.
ومن ثم حاولت ان تطعمني اياها بقوة .. واخذت تدفعني
She's trying to force-feed my camera,
وحاولت اطعام كميرتي
which is every photographer's dream.
وهذا حلم كل مصور
And she would get frustrated; she'd blow bubbles in my face.
ومن ثم بدأت تتعب .. واخذت تنفث الفقاعات على وجهي
She would, I think, let me know that I was going to starve.
واعتقد انها كانت تحاول ان تشرح لي انني سوف اموت من الجوع
But yet she didn't stop.
ولكنها لم تستسلم
She would not stop trying to feed me penguins.
ولم تتوقف عن محاولة اطعامي
And on the last day with this female
وفي آخر يوم مع هذه الانثى
where I thought I had pushed her too far,
عندما ادركت انها شعرت انه قد طفح الكيل
I got nervous because she came up to me,
بدات اتوتر ..عندما اخذت بالاقتراب مني
she rolled over on her back,
ومن قلبت نفسها
and she did this deep, guttural jackhammer sound, this gok-gok-gok-gok.
واصدرت صوتاً عميقاً مثل ارتطام المطرقة مثل " جوك .جوك جوك "
And I thought, she's about to bite.
وقلت في نفسي .. يبدو انها سوف تقوم بعضي الآن
She's about to let me know she's too frustrated with me.
وهي على وشك ان تقول لي قد طفح الكيل
What had happened was another seal had snuck in behind me,
ولكن ما كان يحدث في الحقيقة هو وجود فهد بحر آخر خلفي
and she did that to threat display.
وكان تحاول ان تخيفه وتهدده
She chased that big seal away, went and got its penguin
ومن ثم لاحقت فهد البحر الآخر واخذت البطريق الذي اقتنصه من حصتها
and brought it to me.
واحضرته لي مرة اخرى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That wasn't the only seal I got in the water with.
ولم تكن فهدة البحر تلك الوحيدة التي غصت بالقرب منها
I got in the water with 30 other leopard seals,
بل قمت بذلك مع 30 فهد بحر
and I never once had a scary encounter.
ولم يحدث لي اي موقف خطر طيلة تلك الفترة
They are the most remarkable animals I've ever worked with,
انها حيوانات مميزة جداً .. وافضل الحيوانات التي عملت معها
and the same with polar bears.
وهي مميزة مثل دببة القطب
And just like the polar bears,
وكما دببة القطب
these animals depend on an icy environment.
فهذه الحيوانات تعتمد على البيئة الجليدية
I get emotional. Sorry.
اعذروني .. قد ظهرت عواطفي ..
It's a story that lives deep in my heart,
انها قصة تقطن في قلبي
and I'm proud to share this with you.
وانا فخور لانني اشارككم بها
And I'm so passionate about it.
وانا ملهم جداً بهذه المواقف
Anybody want to come with me to Antarctica or the Arctic, I'll take you; let's go.
واي احد يريد ان ياتي معي الى القطب .. ساسعد باصطحابه
We've got to get the story out now. Thank you very much.
والان لدينا جميعاً قصة علينا نشرها .. شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً
Thank you. Thanks very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم .. شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا